Guide to the Outpunk Archive, 1989-1998 MSS.297
Fales Library and Special Collections
Outpunk Archive
1989-1998
Fales Library and Special Collections
Wobensmith, Matt
Outpunk
MSS.297
4.5 linear feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 2 small flat boxes, and 1 oversize flat box
Founded by Matt Wobensmith, Outpunk was both a zine, published from 1992-1997, and a queercore record label, releasing music from 1992-1998. This collection contains original masters for almost all of the Outpunk zines, as well as a wide variety of documentation about the bands represented by the Outpunk label, including posters, fliers, photographs, and audio recordings.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Outpunk Archive was donated by Matt Wobensmith in 2010, with an accretion to the collection donated in February 2017. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2010.297 and 2017.086, respectively.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into three series: I. Zines, II. Music, III. Phonograph Records, and IV. Ephemera and Objects. Some series have been further arranged into subseries.
Items have been arranged with the original order kept intact; the only exceptions are oversized and dimensional materials, which are housed in separate containers.
Biographical/Historical note
In the early 1990s, the queercore movement was small and largely underground. Matt Wobensmith's writing on the subject, along with his subsequent foray into making queercore music more widely available, gave the movement a more public voice.
Inspired by the Riot Grrrl movement, Wobensmith latched on to the burgeoning DIY culture and translated it into an exploration of the styles, trends, and sounds of the queer, hardcore community by publishing seven issues of the Outpunk zine between 1992-1997. Outpunk zines discussed queer culture, punk rock music, sexual politics, the gay skinhead movement, and feminism.
As a record label, Outpunk provided exposure to queer-focused bands including Tribe 8, Pansy Division, the Mukilteo Fairies, Cypher in the Snow, Sta-Prest, and Behead the Prophet No Lord Shall Live.
After ending both the zine and the record label in the late 1990s, Matt Wobensmith remained involved with zine culture. Today he owns and operates Goteblüd, a zine store and archive in San Francisco.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audio materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Scope and Contents
The Outpunk Archive contains paper files, photographs and audio recordings relating to both Outpunk the zine and Outpunk, the queercore music label. These files include original artwork and flats for Outpunk zines; some administrative records; correspondence between the founder, Matt Wobensmith, and other artists; photographs of artists; copies of Outpunk record releases; and miscellaneous materials that arrived with the collection.
Fliers (printed matter); Riot grrrl movement.; T-shirts; Photographs.; Punk rock music.; Clippings (information artifacts); Zines; Phonograph records.; Punk culture.; Lesbian musicians; Gay musicians; Sexual minorities -- Identity; Outpunk; Wobensmith, Matt; Outpunk; Tribe 8 (Musical group)
- Series I: Zines
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains original flats (master copies) and finished copies of zines created by Matt Wobensmith, as well as some others submitted for distribution by Outpunk.
  - Subseries A: Outpunk Issues
    - Outpunk #1, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Outpunk #1 Original Flat, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Outpunk #2/Fembot, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Outpunk #2 Original Flat, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Outpunk #2 1/2, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Outpunk #2 1/2 Original Flat, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Outpunk #3, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Outpunk #3 Original Flat, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Outpunk #5, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Outpunk #5 Art/Design, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Outpunk #6, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Outpunk #7, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Outpunk Zine Invoices & Correspondence, 1992-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries B: Other Zines
    - "Victoria's Secret Riot Presents Club Death" Original Flat, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Now I Don the Mask of Melancholy #4, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The GSM #4 Original Flat, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Gaybee III Original Flat, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Music
  This series contains documentation, photography, invoices, and correspondence pertaining to bands whose work was distributed by or related to the Outpunk label. Bands include Tribe 8, Team Dresch, Pansy Division, God is My Co-Pilot, and Cyryus.
  - Subseries A: Bands and Promo Materials
    - Outpunk Contracts, 1993-2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Tribe 8, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Tribe 8 Press Kit, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Tribe 8 /Out13 7"/CD5, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - God is My Co-Pilot, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - OPD Lyrics, Graphics, Photos, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Hyperdrive Kittens, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - There's a Dyke in the Pit Promo Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cyryus, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sta-Prest Press, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Tribute to Outpunk Flier, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - BTPNLSL Press, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Band Photos, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General Outpunk Press, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Handbills & Promo Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Misc. Fliers, Clippings, Etc. [1 of 2], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Misc. Fliers, Clippings, Etc. [2 of 2], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Miscellaneous Documentation and Articles
    - QC 101, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - QC 102, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Dirty Bird '96, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Gay Hip Hop Articles, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Misc Articles [1 of 2], 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Misc Articles [2 of 2], undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fliers, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - M. W. Press [1 of 2], 1992-2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - M. W. Press [2 of 2], 1992-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - M. W. Address/Note Book, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous Photos
    - Miscellaneous Photos [1 of 2], undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Photos [2 of 2], undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 2017 Accretion: Photographs, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
- Series III: Phonograph Records
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audio materials are not accessible for listening.
  This series contains albums released by the Outpunk label. Bands include Tribe 8, Cypher in the Snow, God is My Co-Pilot, Hyperdrive Kittens, Pansy Division, and Sta-Prest.
  - Subseries A: Originals
    - Behead the Prophet No Lord Shall Live 7" EP, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Cypher in the Snow "Badass" 7" EP (Test Pressing), undated (Box 4)
    - God is My Co-Pilot/Fifth Column "Don't" 7" EP test pressing, undated (Box 4)
    - Hyperdrive Kittens "Rock 'n' Roll Drag Queen" 7" EP, undated (Box 4)
    - The Need 7" EP test pressing, 1997 (Box 4)
    - The Mukilteo Fairies "Closet Check" 7" EPs, undated (Box 4)
    - Pansy Division "Bill & Ted's Homosexual Adventure" 7" EP test pressing, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Pansy Division "Nine Inch Males" 7" EP, undated (Box 4)
    - Sta-Prest "Let's Be Friendly with Our Friends" 7" EP and test pressing, undated (Box 4)
    - Sta-Prest "Vespa Sex" 7" EP, undated (Box 4)
    - Team Dresch "the new TEAM DRESCH v. 6.0 beta" 7" EP test pressing, undated (Box 4)
    - "There's a Dyke in the Pit" 7" Compilation EP, undated (Box 4)
    - "There's a Dyke in the Pit" 7" Compilation EP test pressing, undated (Box 4)
    - "There's a Faggot in the Pit" 7" Compilation EP, 1991 (Box 4)
    - Tribe 8 self-titled 7" EP, 1994 (Box 4)
- Series IV: Ephemera and Objects
  This series contains oversize photography, posters, and artwork, as well as a collection of band t-shirts and a skateboard.
  - Subseries A: Fliers, Clippings, Photos, and Artwork
    - Misc. Clippings, Fliers, Etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 1, Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Photography, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Posters, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Tribe 8 Poster Mounted on Foam Core, undated (Box 8)
  - Subseries B: T-shirts and Artifacts
    - Pansy Division promotional box, undated (Box 4, Object ID: 297.2.0001)
    - Punk Beat "Where the Boys Are" t-shirt, undated (Box 5, Object ID: 297.2.0002)
    - God is My Co-Pilot "make Queer theory" t-shirt, undated (Box 5, Object ID: 297.2.0003)
    - The Mukilteo Fairies t-shirt, undated (Box 5, Object ID: 297.2.0004)
    - Tribe 8 t-shirt, undated (Box 5, Object ID: 297.2.0005)
    - Brat Attack "Bad Girls Rule" t-shirt, undated (Box 6, Object ID: 297.2.0006)
    - Behead the Prophet No Lord Shall Live t-shirt, undated (Box 6, Object ID: 297.2.0007)
    - Sta-Prest "In Control of Your Comfort" t-shirt, undated (Box 6, Object ID: 297.2.0008)
    - Behead the Prophet dress shirt with tie, undated (Box 7, Object ID: 297.2.0009)
    - Skateboard, undated (Oversize ID: 297.2.0010)